William R. Mathews papers 1870-1980
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
William R. Mathews papers 1870-1980
MS 406
Matthews, William R.
The William R. Mathews papers (1870-1980) primarily documents his journalism career as editor and publisher of the Arizona Daily Star (1930-1967). The collection also includes material relating to Mathews' military service in World War I, and his role as an official war correspondent in World War II. Also included are the family papers of William R. Mathews and his wife, Betty B. Mathews.
18.0 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
William R. Mathews (1893-1969) was an accomplished journalist, newspaper editor and publisher. Born in Lexington, Kentucky in 1893, he attended elementary and high school in Indianapolis, Indiana, and graduated with an A.B. degree in Money and Banking from the University of Illinois in 1917. He served as a Second Lieutenant and Captain in the Fifth Regiment of the Second Division of the United States Marine Corps during World War I. He fought in the battles of Belleau Wood and Soissons, in France, and was wounded in the attack on Blanc Mont. Mr. Mathews earned numerous awards and citations, including the French Croix de Guerre with Palm, in 1918, for capturing 75 German soldiers. After the war he worked as an advertising solicitor for the San Francisco Chronicle. He married Betty Boyers, in 1919, and they had four children. From 1920-1924, he was the business manager of the Santa Barbara Morning Press. In 1924, he and business partner Ralph E. Ellinwood purchased the Arizona Daily Star in Tucson, Arizona. Mr. Mathews served as the general manager from 1924-1930 and as editor and publisher from 1930-1967.
Mr. Mathews' extensive travels enabled him to focus his journalism on international politics and foreign affairs. He served as an accredited military correspondent and completed nine trips around the world. He witnessed and documented unique historical events, such as the signing of the Japanese Surrender aboard the U.S.S. Missouri in 1945, the Bikini Bomb Test in 1946 and the John Foster Dulles trip to Japan and Korea, just prior to the outbreak of the Korean Conflict. Mr. Mathews was active in public service and his appointments include: special adviser to James B. Forrestal, Secretary of Defense (1948-1950), member of the Pulitzer Prize Committee, member of the Board of Regents of the University of Arizona, and Chairman of the Citizens' Public Utilities and Citizens' Water Advisory Committees for the City of Tucson. In 1940 he ran for public office as a democratic representative for Congress.
Organization
This collection is organized into 12 series. 3 series contain subseries: Writings, Photographs and Scrapbooks.
Series 1: Biographical files, 1925-1971
Series 2: Correspondence files, 1924-1969
Series 3: Writings, 1919-1967
Subseries 1: Articles and editorials, 1919-1967
Subseries 2: Oversize articles and editorials, 1937-1949
Subseries 3: Manuscripts, 1939-1962
Series 4: Speech files, 1937-1967
Series 5: Public Service, 1926-1964
Series 6: Travel files, 1937-1968
Series 7: Photographs, 1886-1980
Subseries 1: General, 1886-circa 1940
Subseries 2: Albums, 1928-1969
Subseries 3: Oversize, 1943-1980
Series 8: Scrapbooks, 1916-1968
Subseries 1: Military, 1916-1968
Subseries 2: Newspaper clippings, 1942-1968
Subseries 3: Travel and event, 1945-1950, 1967
Series 9: William R. Mathews family papers, 1939-1966
Series 10: Betty B. Mathews family papers, 1870-1975
Series 11: Newspaper clippings, 1949-1974
Series 12: Ledgers, 1916-undated
Scope and Content Note
The William R. Mathews papers (1870-1980) primarily document his journalism career as editor and publisher of the Arizona Daily Star (1930-1967), and also includes material relating to Mathews' military service in World War I, and his role as an official war correspondent in World War II. These papers also contain the family papers of William R. Mathews as well as those of his wife, Betty B. Mathews. This collection consists of biographical information, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, writings, speeches, public service files, travel files, family papers, ledgers, and newspaper clippings.
Access Terms
Matthews, William R.
Matthews, Betty B.
Arizona Daily Star -- History -- Sources.
Journalists -- Arizona.
Newspaper editors.
War correspondents -- United States.
Correspondence
Scrapbooks
Ledgers
Photographs
Container List
- Biographical files, 1925-1971, Series I:
  Biographical files document Mr. Mathew's military service and accomplishments, along with his experience and achievements as a newspaper journalist, editor and publisher. They include personal and professional recollections and discussions of significant national and international events and leaders during the early to mid-twentieth century. His public service activities at the local, state and national levels are also documented in this series, as well as litigation against the state of Arizona for access to public information. Arrangement is alphabetical.
  - Arizona Daily Star stationery, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography; chapters I-VII, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiography; chapters VIII-XVI, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autobiography; revision, chapters I-XVI, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autobiography; rough draft, chapters I-XVI, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cartoon by Thomoson of William R. Mathews in WWI, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of retirement; Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marine Corps Reserve 50th Anniversary commemorative postage stamp, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mathews for Congress pamphlet, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mathews, William R; Articles about, 1940-1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mathews, William R. vs. Governor of State of Arizona, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Military Records and correspondence, 1925-1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Obituaries, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Special Navy consultant, 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence files, 1929-1969, Series II:
  Correspondence files primarily document Mr. Mathews' professional communication with colleagues and local, state, national and international political and military leaders and other notable individuals. Correspondence in his capacity as editor of the Arizona Daily Star is also included. Some files contain research information and news articles by William R. Mathews. Arrangement is alphabetical.
  - American National Red Cross, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Arizona Daily Star, 1924-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arizona State Welfare Board, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Arizona Tax Research Association, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Astor, David, 1935-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Atomic Energy Commission, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bohlen, Charles, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bolin, Wesley, 1949-1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Butler University, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Central Intelligence Agency; J.E. Hoover and A. Dulles, 1951-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Clay, Lucius D., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cusick, Watkins and Frey, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Daniels, Josephus, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dawes, General Charles G., 1936-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dulles, John Foster, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Eisenhower, President Dwight D., 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Forrestal, James; Secretary of Defense, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fredericks, Pierce G., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fund for the Republic Inc., 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Garvey, Dan, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General, (1 of 3) 1957-1968 (Box 1a, Folder 1)
  - General, (2 of 3) 1957-1968 (Box 1a, Folder 2)
  - General, (3 of 3) 1957-1968 (Box 1a, Folder 3)
  - Goldwater, Barry, 1952-1964 (Box 1a, Folder 4)
  - Goldwater, Barry, (1 of 2) 1952-1969 (Box 1a, Folder 5)
  - Goldwater, Barry, (2 of 2) 1952-1969 (Box 1a, Folder 6)
  - Grand Canyon Dams, 1950-1966 (Box 1a, Folder 7)
  - Great Leaders, 1934-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hadow, R.H., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Halifax, H.E. and Lady, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Harbord, James G., 1924-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hayden, Carl, 1939-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Hayden, Carl, 1956-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - Hayden, Carl; Budget Letters, 1935-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Inskeep Resignation, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - International Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Janeway, Eliot, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Kennedy, John. F. 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Keyser, Ralph S., 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Kissinger, Henry, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kitchel, Denison, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Krock, Arthur, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Landon, Alf M., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lewis, Anthony, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lilienthal, Alfred M., 1940-1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mannini-Klafter Realty, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Marines, 1917-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Marshall, George C., 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - McFarland, Ernest, 1942-1963 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - McNamara, Robert S., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Morgenthau, Henry Jr., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - National Press Club, 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Navy Department, 1949-1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper Editors, 1940-1965 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1942-1967 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Nixon, Richard M. 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Osborn, Sidney P., 1941-1947 (Box 2a, Folder 1)
  - P., (1 of 3) 1945-1959 (Box 2a, Folder 2)
  - P., (2 of 3) 1945-1959 (Box 2a, Folder 3)
  - P., (3 of 3) 1945-1959 (Box 2a, Folder 4)
  - Patten, Harold A. (Porque), 1949-1958 (Box 2a, Folder 5)
  - Pegler, Westbrook, 1941-1962 (Box 2a, Folder 6)
  - Perkins, Milo. 1961 (Box 2a, Folder 7)
  - Pershing, John J., 1936-1960 (Box 2a, Folder 8)
  - Phoenix, Arizona, 1940-1963 (Box 2a, Folder 9)
  - Phoenix newspapers, 1949-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Powell River company, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Presidential election predictions, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Presidential candidates and possibilities, 1943-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Primary gubernatorial campaigns, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pulitzer, Joseph, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Prisoners of war, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pyle, Howard, 1950-1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - R., 1944-1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ramey, Roger, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Rankin Family, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reston, James, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rhodes, John J., 1953-1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Rockefeller, John D. III., 1952-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Romine, L.A., 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1931-1943 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Rosenberg, Anna M., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Rougeron, Camille. 1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - S., 1941-1960 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - S., 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Sale of Arizona Daily Star, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Salzberger, Arthur Ochs, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Santa Barbara Daily News, 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Schlager, Sig, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Schweitzer, Albert, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Sedgwick, Ellery, 1936-1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Sen, Sachin; Visit to Tucson, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Shepherd, Lemuel C., 1935-1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Slee, Margaret Sanger, 1949-1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Small loan companies, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Smith, Howard J., 1953 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Smith, Ralph C., 1950 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Social security and welfare, 1942-1958 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - South American tabloid, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Special Senate Committee Testimony, 1940-1957 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - State Department, 1938-1954 (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  - State Department, 1956-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stauffer, Oscar; Menninger Foundation, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stitt, Phil, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Stocker, Joseph, 1949-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stolpe, Bert, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Swanson, Theodore and company, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Swinehart, Gerry, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Symington, Stuart W., 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - T., 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Tabloid requests, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Taft, Robert A., 1949-1952 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Telegrams, 1921-1941 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Thacher, A.G., 1931-1955 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Thomason, John William, Jr. 1940-1955 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, 1944-1959 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "German recovery", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "Indonesia", 1949-1952 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "Moderation in Japan urged", 1945 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "Repatriating prisoners", 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "Report from Tucson on foreign policy", 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Times Letters to the editor; "Tucson Looks at the World", 1953 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Times Letters to the Editor; "Use of atomic energy", 1954 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Townley, Josephine, 1929-1954 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1945-1951 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Turner, Lillian, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Udall, Congressman Stewart L., 1949-1959 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Udall, Congressman Morris K., 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - U.S. High Commissioner for Germany, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Vanderbilt, Neil, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Von Royen, J.H., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - W., 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
  - Waldman, Louis, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Wall Street Journal; "By Our Silence", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - War College, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - War Department, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - War Department; censorship, 1940-1948 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - War predictions, 1938-1945 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Wedemeyer, A.L., 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - White House, 1953-1965 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Whitton, Margaret, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Williams, Herschel, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Wilson, Delmar E., 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Wilson, Lyle C., 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Wolff, Robert, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Writings, 1919-1967, Series III:
  This series is divided into three subseries: Articles and Editorials (1919-1967), Oversize Articles and Editorials (1937-1949), and Manuscripts (1939-1962). Articles and Editorials includes writings by Mr. Mathews, primarily in his capacity as editor of the Arizona Daily Star, documenting his interviews with notable individuals, global travels, and local, state, national and international affairs and politics. The arrangement is alphabetical with the bulk of this series organized chronologically under the 'General' category. Manuscripts include several revised and re-titled versions of Mr. Mathews' unpublished book on his military and other professional experiences.
  - Articles and Editorials; 1919-1967, Subseries 1:
    - "30 Days in Equatorial Africa", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Age of Continents", 1956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Are We Being Shouted Into an Unwanted War?", 1951 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Arizona and the Colorado", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Australia and New Zealand, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Awakening of South America", 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Battle of Belleau Wood", 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Battle of Belleau Wood-Research, 1919-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8-12)
    - England, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Europe Will Recover", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - European Trip, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - General, 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 16-21)
    - General, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - General, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - General, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 24-26)
    - General, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - General, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - General, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - General 1951 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - General, 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - General, 1957-1961 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Indonesia Report," Foreward 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Interview with General Douglas MacArthur", 1945-1955 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Let's Remember the Rule of Law", 1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Letter to the New President"; The Atlantic Monthly, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Letters to the Times; "Use of Atomic Energy", 1954 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Marines WWII Battles Detailed", 1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "Marshall Plan Pays Off", 1951 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Pan-American; Lima, Peru, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Peace by Negotiation and the Press", 1954 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "Prediction of Soviet Intentions", 1945 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Prelude to War", 1939 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Public Utilities Purchase, 1943-1948 (Box 6, Folder 21-24)
    - Pulitzer, Joseph, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Republican Convention, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - "Roundup, 10 Days Behind the Iron Curtain", 1954 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Russia, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Russian Trip, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - "Senator Robert Taft Dying of Cancer", 1953 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - South America, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Sunland Gardens, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1942-1960 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings Comments, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Viet Nam, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - "War with Japan", 1966 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - "We Conquer Japan", 1945 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - "Weapon That Will Prolong the War", 1942 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - "When F.D.R. Was Floored", 1958 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - "When Peace Breaks Out: Can We Afford It?", 1959 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - "Why Not Learn From Our Experiences", 1960 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Wilson vs. State Consolidated and Morrison. 1952 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - "With Dulles in Korea and Japan", 1967 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Oversize Articles and Editorials, 1937-1949, Subseries 2:
    - "Around the Seething World", 1937 (Box 6a)
    - "Europe Goes Goosestep", 1935 (Box 6a)
    - "Arizona and the Colorado", 1944 (Box 6a)
    - "England at War", 1942 (Box 6a)
    - "We Conquer Japan", 1945 (Box 6a)
    - "Europe Will Recover", 1947 (Box 6a)
    - "Europe Will Recover", 1949 (Box 6a)
  - Manuscripts, 1939-1962, Subseries 3:
    - "America Cannot Escape History", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Chapters I-VII, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Chapters VIII-XX, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Chapter VIII "Germany and Synthetic Character", 1961 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Miscellaneous Chapters, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Original Draft, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Research, 1939-1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Research about Raw Materials, 1939-1944 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Research, Population Association of America, 1943-1954 (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - "America Cannot Escape History"; Research, Population Reference Bureau, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 11-13)
    - "America Will Make, Not Escape History", undated (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
    - "America Will Make, Not Escape History"; Incomplete undated (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
    - "America Will Make, Not Escape, History", 1962 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - "America Will Make, Not Escape History"; Chapters VI- XV, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - "America Will Make, Not Escape History"; Autobiographical version, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - "Brief Summary of Belleau Wood", 1959 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "Coming of Medical Education to Arizona", undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Speech Files, 1937-1967, Series IV:
  This series includes professional and public speeches, primarily on national and international affairs. The arrangement is alphabetical with the bulk of this series organized chronologically under the 'General' category.
  - "America Marches on to its Destiny", 1962 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "An American Empire?", 1958 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Channel Club, Santa Barbara, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Food, People and War", undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - General, 1937-1940 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - General, 1942-1949 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - General, 1950-1966 (Box 8, Folder 9-12)
  - General Shepherd's Remarks at Dinner for Bill Mathews, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Mathews Candidate for Congress, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Other Authors, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Radio Broadcasts, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Recent Travels and Observations in the Middle East"; Tucson Committee on Foreign Relations, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - "Resume of War"; Rotary Club, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - "South Viet Nam and American Destiny", 1966 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "Spanish Element in Our Nationality"; Speech to Spanish Americans, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - "Yalta Conference", 1945 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Public Service Files, 1926-1964, Series V:
  This series documents Mr. Mathews' local, state and national public service activities, including his campaign for Congress in 1940. Arrangement is alphabetical.
  - Arizona State Office Building Committee, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Board of Governors; Federal Reserve System, 1958-1963 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Board of Regents; University and State Colleges of Arizona, 1949-1961 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Board of Regents; University and State Colleges of Arizona- Meeting Agendas, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Campaign for Congress; Publicity. 1940 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Campaign for Congress; Republican Hand Bill, 1940-1944 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Citizens' Advisory Water Committee, 1930-1951 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Citizens' Advisory Water Committee, 1940-1949 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Citizens' Advisory Water Committee; Avra-Altar Valley Water, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee, 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Arizona Corporation Commission Hearing, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Arizona Edison Company, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Arizona Power Authority, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Bond Houses, 1942-1945 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Central Arizona Light and Power Company, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Charter Amendment, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; City Attorney, 1940-1947 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Electric Power Board of Chattanooga, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Engineering Firms, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Federal Light and Traction Company, 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Federal Power Commission, 1938-1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Holding Companies, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Citizens' Public Utilities Committee; Information from Other Cities, Re: Boards, 1929-1943 (Box 9, Folder 6)